<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Home Page on Daniel Alemayehu</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in The Home Page on Daniel Alemayehu</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>© 2025 Daniel Alemayehu</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>CEM Fall 2024 Article</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/cem-spring-2025-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/cem-spring-2025-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;&#xA;Preface&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I wrote this article for the Spring 2025 edition of the Colorado Engineering Magazine which focused on the intersection between technology and nature. In alignment with this I wrote about Dr. Peleg&amp;#39;s research at CU Boulder which intersects between computer science, conservational biology, and mathematical modelling.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;Below is a transcript of the article. The article is also published &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.colorado.edu/studentgroups/colorado-engineer/2024/green-energy&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and I encourage you to read the other CEM articles linked found there as well!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symposium Speech</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/symposium-speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/symposium-speech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;&#xA;Introduction:&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As a part of my freshman seminar class EHON 1151 our professor Scot Douglass asked us to come up with our own ideas regarding the concept of love and to share this with a small group of our peers over a home cooked dinner party, in the spirit of the events of &lt;em&gt;Symposium&lt;/em&gt; by Plato. I share a transcript of my speech below in which I share my ideas regarding how one can distinguish between different types of love and critique how love is commonly recognized modernly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jerrimeter</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/jerrimeter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/jerrimeter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MatthewStuckenbruck/t9-hacks-2025&#34;&gt;View Source Code and Documentation Here!&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the 2025 T9-MediHacks me and a team of 4 others developed a password analyzer in 24 hours that measured the strength of an input string as a password, complete as a simple web-page that requires no hosting to run allowing any user to simply pick up and learn more about password security and information theory!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;This placed first in the cybersecurity track of the competition netting our team Raspberry Pis 4B kits!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the Mariana Trench</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/analyzing-the-mariana-trench/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/analyzing-the-mariana-trench/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DTAlemayehu01/APPM2360-Project2&#34;&gt;View Project Source Here!&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For our APPM 2360 class at CU Boulder, me and two partners studied the Incomplete SVD and how it can be used to take complex data sets and make it easier to study by reducing the amount of memory used to represent that data. We also studied different sizes of Incomplete SVDs and the tradeoffs in data resolution as we increased the number of eigenvalues used in our Incomplete SVD.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CEM Fall 2024 Article</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/cem-fall-2024-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/cem-fall-2024-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;&#xA;Preface&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I wrote this article for the Fall 2024 edition of the Colorado Engineering Magazine which focused on future technologies and possible futures available with current technologies. In alignment with this I wrote about the Fediverse and how it could serve as a future platform for social interaction that goes beyond traditional social media (Youtube, Snapchat, Instagram, Etc.).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;Below is a transcript of the article.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;The Fediverse and the Future of Social Connection&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;“Platform decay” is the term social media users have used to describe the progression of social platforms over time. Cory Doctorow, the Electronic Frontier Foundation Special Advisor, writes about the degenerating state of the company sponsored platforms like X (formerly Twitter), Instagram, and Snapchat from originally serving as places of online connection to that of a delivery platform for advertisements straight to the consumer. For Doctrow, this degeneration is a given considering these platforms don’t follow the two key principles he’s identified for running a positive social platform:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trout Population Modeling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/trout-population-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/trout-population-modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DTAlemayehu01/APPM2360-Project1/&#34;&gt;View Project Source Here!&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For our APPM 2360 class at CU Boulder, me and my partner modeled predicted trout populations in a pond from a given neighborhood in order to create an informed decision as to how to best stock the pond with fish to maximize the enjoyment from fishing in the pond any neighborhood participants may have. We modeled the trout in a variety of ways through MATLAB code and the modified Logistic Growth Equation for each trout spieces we analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Safer Scientific Computing In Rust</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/cu-spur-rust/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/cu-spur-rust/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&#xA;In the CU SPUR program I worked with Professor Jed Brown to investigate the capabilities of the Rust programming language in the field of Scientific Computation through analyzing rootfinding/optimization libraries in C, comparing them to the similar libraries in Rust, and then taking advantage of the FFI to combine the capabilities of current C libraries and the security and semantic clarity of Rust libraries.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;To study scientific computation in both languages we analyzed the Cohesive Zone problem which describes how materials respond with adhesives under certain amounts of internal force. In the diagram below we have a simple depicition of the cohesive zone phenomenon. The important note below is that materials don&amp;#39;t immediately split apart but slightly deform when pulled apart until the adhesive is unable to hold the materials together creating a &amp;#34;snap-back&amp;#34; effect where the material returns to its original state. The point right before this snap-back is our stable equilibrium we sought to identify in our iterative solving methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Music Merge</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/music-merge/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/music-merge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/CSCI-3308-Group-014-06-Final-Project/Music-Merge&#34;&gt;View Source Code and Documentation Here!&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For the final project in CU Boulder&amp;#39;s CSCI 3308 class me and a team of 5 others utilized the public Spotify API in order to help users manage their playlists better in a simple frontend. The Spotify app does have utilities to merge two playlists but we extend this functionality to multiple playlists and provide settings for users to set attributes for their next merged playlist.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
