<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Articles on Daniel Alemayehu</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Articles on Daniel Alemayehu</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>© 2025 Daniel Alemayehu</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>CEM Fall 2024 Article</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/cem-spring-2025-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/cem-spring-2025-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;&#xA;Preface&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I wrote this article for the Spring 2025 edition of the Colorado Engineering Magazine which focused on the intersection between technology and nature. In alignment with this I wrote about Dr. Peleg&amp;#39;s research at CU Boulder which intersects between computer science, conservational biology, and mathematical modelling.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;Below is a transcript of the article. The article is also published &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.colorado.edu/studentgroups/colorado-engineer/2024/green-energy&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and I encourage you to read the other CEM articles linked found there as well!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symposium Speech</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/symposium-speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/symposium-speech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;&#xA;Introduction:&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As a part of my freshman seminar class EHON 1151 our professor Scot Douglass asked us to come up with our own ideas regarding the concept of love and to share this with a small group of our peers over a home cooked dinner party, in the spirit of the events of &lt;em&gt;Symposium&lt;/em&gt; by Plato. I share a transcript of my speech below in which I share my ideas regarding how one can distinguish between different types of love and critique how love is commonly recognized modernly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CEM Fall 2024 Article</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/cem-fall-2024-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/cem-fall-2024-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;&#xA;Preface&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I wrote this article for the Fall 2024 edition of the Colorado Engineering Magazine which focused on future technologies and possible futures available with current technologies. In alignment with this I wrote about the Fediverse and how it could serve as a future platform for social interaction that goes beyond traditional social media (Youtube, Snapchat, Instagram, Etc.).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;Below is a transcript of the article.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;The Fediverse and the Future of Social Connection&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;“Platform decay” is the term social media users have used to describe the progression of social platforms over time. Cory Doctorow, the Electronic Frontier Foundation Special Advisor, writes about the degenerating state of the company sponsored platforms like X (formerly Twitter), Instagram, and Snapchat from originally serving as places of online connection to that of a delivery platform for advertisements straight to the consumer. For Doctrow, this degeneration is a given considering these platforms don’t follow the two key principles he’s identified for running a positive social platform:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
